沃里克郡 康普顿-怀内特斯
COMPTON WYNATES WARWICKSBIRE.
威廉爵士…
Sir william…
威廉爵士 您怎么了？
sir william! What is it?
找医生来 快
Go and fetch the physician! Go and get him! Now!
老天 为何没人叫醒他？
Good god, man: Why did no one wake him?!
这种情况下 睡眠是致命的
Sleep in these cases is fatal.
走开 走开 蠢人们
Keep away! Keep away, you fools!
你们主子得了汗热病
Your master has the sweating sickness.
哦
Oh!
你俩… 你 留下
You two… you stay!
得试试救救他… 可怜人啊
We must try and treat him… poor fellow.
给他翻身
Turn him over!
行行好 你们就忍着吧
For the love of god, get on with it!
或许还有救
We may yet save him.
我要刺入他的背部
I'm going to cut into his back,
因为我听说这方法有时有效
for I heard that it sometimes works,
能让毒素流出体外
it draws off some of the toxin.
抓好他
Hold him now!
你来做什么？
What are you doing?
我不能见他吗？
May I not meet him?
上帝啊 女人… 出去 出去
God, woman. Out! Out!
国王陛下及安-博林女士到
His majesty the king and lady anne boleyn.
沃尔西
Wolsey.
陛下
Your majesty.
安女士 衷心欢迎你
Mistress anne. You are most welcome.
非常感谢主教阁下 送给我如此精美的胸针
I must thank your eminence for the magnificent brooch you sent me.
你喜欢就太好了
I am so glad you liked it.
它是意大利风格的 我认为它的工艺实在高超
It is italianate, I thought the craftsmanship superb.
我相信陛下也会同样开心
And I'm sure your majesty will be equally pleased.
能收到法兰西国王的礼物
with the presents sent by the king of france:
一只黄金圣杯
A golden chalice!|能收到法兰西国王的礼物|with the presents sent by the king of france:
A golden chalice!
金丝编织的布料
Gold silk altar cloths!
还有价值至少3万达克特的织锦
And tapestries worth, I'm sure at least 30, 000 ducats!
那么我们便与法国再次结盟了
So we are once more allies with the french.
的确 并且英法两国 都正式对罗马皇帝宣战
Indeed. And we are both officially at war with the emperor.
好 我很满意
Good. It pleases me.
皇帝他肯定也很满意 因为他宣告天下他刚得了个儿子
As it pleased the emperor to announce that he has just had a son!
还是他抛弃我女儿另娶的 那个公主所生
By the princess he jilted my daughter for!
你会有儿子的
You'll have a son.
你觉得这虾怎么样 安女士？
How's the shrimp, lady anne?
非常美味 阁下 谢谢
Perfect, your eminence. Thank you.
您太慷慨了 任何方面都是
You are too generous. In everything.
那 我们的私事如何了？
So, what of our personal matter?
陛下 我已安排派出两位同僚
Your majesty, I have arranged to send 2 of my colleagues,
两位年轻律师
2 young lawyers,
斯蒂·加德纳 我的秘书 及爱德华·福克斯
stephen gardiner, my secretary, and edward foxe,
前去罗马附近的奥维多会见教皇 他现在居住在那里
to meet the pope.
老人家显然还在经受不幸的病痛
in wretched discomfort, apparently.
您给这两位律师什么任务？
What will you have these lawyers do?
他们会给教皇陛下强调 配合我们的必要性
My lady, they will press upon his holiness, the necessity of his cooperation.
必须让他意识到 无论从民法还是教规来说
He must recognize, in both civil and canon laws,
陛下您的婚姻都是无效的
the invalidity of your majesty's marriage.
我为这事阅读了无数条文
I have read countless texts on the matter.
有时看到深夜 令到自己头痛不已…
Sometimes reading well into the night and giving myself terrible headaches…
但我比任何时候都确信我的案例
But I am more assured now than ever of the spiritual.
符合教会信条以及法律公正
land egal justice of my case.
我的道德良知非常清晰
My conscience is clear!
的确如此
As it should be.
陛下您可以放心 这两位绅士
And your majesty must rest assured, that these 2 gentlemen,
这两位永不停歇的律师
these 2 restless lawyers,
在得到满意答复前不会离开奥维多
will not leave orvieto until they have attained satisfaction.
好 很好
Good. Very good.
近来你和国王有过交谈吗？
HAVE YOU SPOKEN RECETLY WITH THE KING?
没有 陛下
NO, YOUR MAJESTY.
沃尔西主教拒绝我的求见 并且十分高姿态
CARDINAL WOLSEY REFUSES MY REPUWSTS, AND IN A MOST HIGH HANDED MANNER…
我知道英国人有个特点
IT IS SOMETHING I HAVE LEARNED ABOUT THE ENGLISH.
小小得意就能让他们飞扬跋扈
A SMALL ADVANTAGE MAKES THEM OVERBEARING,
微不足道的难事也能让他们彻底沮丧
WHILE THE SLIGHTEST ADVERSITY MAKES THEM DESPONGDENT.
我收到一封您侄儿 皇帝陛下的密信
I HAVE RECEIBED A CODED LETTER FROM YOUR NEPHEW, THE EMPEROR.
他表示 在这丑恶的事件中 必将给您最坚定的支持
HE DECLARES HIS UNDYING SUPPORT FOR YOU IN THIS UGLY MATTER.
- 你们不用跟来了 - 是 陛下
- You may wait for me year. - Yes, your majesty.
请继续
PRAY CONTINUE.
皇帝陛下已致信克莱门特教皇陛下
HE HAS ALREADY WRITTEN A LETTER TO HIS HOLINESS POPE CLEMENT.
提醒他英国王的野蛮意图
WARNING HIM OF THE KINGS BRUTAL INTENTIONS.
并要求教皇取消沃尔西的继任权
HE HAS ASKED CLEMENT TO DISMISS WOLSEY AS OFFICIAL LEGATE,
宣布您和国王的婚姻是合法有效的
AND DECLARE YOU AND THE KING LEGALLY MARRIDE.
皇帝陛下请您务必坚强
HE TELLS YOU TO BE STRONG.
我尽量
I TRY TO BE.
但我能知道得太少了
BUT SO MUCH NOW IS HIDDEN FROM ME.
请转告他 我信任他胜过任何人
TELL HIM THAT I TRUST IN HIM MORE THAN ANYONE ELSE.
除了上帝
EXCEPT IN GOD.
黑斯廷斯女士
Mistress hastings.
林纳克医生？
Dr. Linacre?
国王陛下一听到消息马上就派了我来 但很遗憾 还是没来得及
As soon as he heard the news,
黑斯廷斯女士 我知道您是他的合法妻子
Mistress hastings I know you were his commonlaw wife.
他无论何时何地 都是一位非常可爱及有爱心的先生
He was in every way, a most lovely and loving man.
国王陛下会万分想念他的陪伴
His majesty will miss his companionship a great deal.
让我看他
Let me see him.
有极大的危险 程度之严重我们无法预测
There is a grave risk. About which we know so little.
求您
Please.
我可怜的 甜蜜的亲爱的人…
My poor, sweet darling…
请原谅 您一定要焚烧掉 他所有的寝具和衣物
Forgive me. You must burn all his bedding and clothing.
现在首要的 是尽快给他下葬
He must be in the ground first thing.
先生们 这是国王给教皇的一封私人信件
Gentlemen, here is a personal letter from the king to the pope,
提前感谢他 带着同情心出席国王的诉讼
thanking him in advance for attending to his suit sympathetically.
教皇陛下有可能如何回应？
How is his holiness likely to respond?
向你实说 加德纳先生 我也不能完全肯定
To be honest with you, mr. Gardiner, I am not absolutely sure.
教皇曾被罗马皇帝雇佣兵施以暴行
The pope was an abused prisoner of the emperor's mercenaries.
即便如此 皇帝仍让他逃到了奥维多
And even though the emperor reputedly allowed him to escape to orvieto,
在那儿 虽然他的状况略有好转
his condition continues to be little better there.
他生活还是比较悲惨 被锁在一座残破的城堡里
He leads a most sad life, locked up in a ruined castle.
这种情况下 教皇为什么会偏向
In which case, why should the pope favour the emperor.
这个让他悲惨不堪的圣罗马皇帝 而不向从未伤害于他的
who has caused him nothing but misery over the king of england,
英国国王靠拢呢
who has never caused him any harm at all?
问题是 主教阁下
The trouble is, your eminence,
英格兰国王的势力比罗马皇帝的
the swords of the king of england are much further away.
要遥远许多
than the swords of the emperor.
外交事宜几乎从来都是 以地域距离决定的
Diplomacy is nearly always settled by such proximity.
的确是律师之见
Spoken like a true lawyer!
万一所有说法都不奏效 就用威胁
But if all else fails, use threats.
告诉教皇陛下 如果我国王 无法从教廷得到满意决断…
Tell his holiness that if the king can't get satisfaction from the papal court…
他会找到其他办法达到目的
he will find other means to satisfy his conscience.
让自己从现在的妻子身边解脱
and rid himself of his present wife.
我说得够明白了吗？
Do I make myself clear?
是 阁下 我们懂了
Yes, eminence. We understand.
快行动吧 先生们
God speed, gentlemen.
威廉去世那晚 仆人们开始偷他的遗物
The evening after william died, his servants began stealing his effects.
他在遗嘱里写了要把这个遗赠予国王
In his will he bequeathed this to the king.
我总算保住了它
I managed to save it.
威廉葬在墓园里
William is buried in the churchyard.
还有那两位可怜的仆人 他们也染了病
So too are the poor servants who also caught.
在之后24小时内也死去了
and died of the sweat in the last 24 hours.
我不知道要跟您说什么
I don't know what to say to you.
威廉-康普顿
WM COMPTON.
诺福克大人
My lord norfolk.
- 主教阁下 - 阁下
- Eminence. - Your eminence.
- 有何贵干？- 跟您说几句 如果可以的话
- What do you want? - A word with you if I might.
- 私下说 - 行
- In private. - Very well.
您被命令 立刻回您东英吉利亚的领地
You are commanded to return at once to your estates in east anglia.
什么？谁的命令？
What? And by whom?
国王陛下
By his majesty.
亲笔写的
In his own hand.
为何？
What for?
陛下希望您能监管粮食生产
His majesty would like you to supervise grain production.
和北海贸易
and north sea trade.
贸易？
Trade?
贸易…
Trade…
你当我是什么？
what do you take me for?
屠夫的儿子？
A butcher's son?!
您也看到了 大人 这并非我的指令
As you see, my lord, these are not my orders.
可怜的威廉
Poor william!
这就是他一生所有的遗物？
Is this all that remains, of an entire life?
你要确保这些珠宝 全数归还他不幸的妻子
We must see that these jewels get back to his unfortunate lady.
威廉是在他沃里克的家中死去的 离这里很远
William died at his house at warwickshire which is a long way from here.
上帝保佑这恶疾不要扩散
and god willing, the disease won't spread.
但你们在任何情况下 都要增强自己的抵抗力
But you should fortify yourselves against it in any case.
这些是医治溃疡的膏药
Now, these are plasters to heal ulcers.
这是种软膏 能清凉灼伤皮肤 还能止痒
This is an unguent, which cools inflammation and stops itching.
这个帮助消化
This helps digestion,
这个润滑干燥皮肤…
this soothes dry skin…
而这种软膏 能缓解阳具疼痛
and this ointment will comfort your cock if it's sore.
谢谢陛下
Thank you.
这些叫做瑞西斯药片
These are called pills of rasis,
是用发明它的土耳其人的名字命名
they're named after the turk who invented them.
据说能对付热汗病
They are said to be good against the sweating sickness.
但这种草药汤剂更有效
But this infusion is even better.
这是什么？
What is it?
是草药混合液 有金盏花
It's a mixture of marigold,
和效用很好的草药
manus christi a very efficacious herb.
酢浆草 牧草
sorrel, meadow plant,
亚麻籽醋 象牙屑
linseed vinegar, ivory scrapings,
全部跟糖混合 试试
all mixed with sugar. Take some.
您确定吗？
Are you sure?
有人告诉过我 喝草药汤剂是最不好的
Someone told me that taking infusions was the worst thing.
相信我
Trust me.
会让你有些反胃
It'll make you feel sick.
但比起它预防的疾病还是好太多了
But it's better than the sickness it prevents!
哦 黑斯廷斯女士
Oh, mistress hastings.
把她葬在威廉爵士旁边
Bury her beside sir william.
真动听
That's so beautiful.
只是一段写给朋友的篇章
It's just something for a friend.
请原谅 我无法工作 除非我…
Forgive me, I can't work, unless I'M…
当然 晚安 托马斯-塔利斯
of course. Good night, thomas tallis.
等等
Wait!
你的名字是？
What's your name?
琼
Joan.
请留一会儿
Stay a moment.
为什么… 是我？
Why… me?
你认为在世人眼中 你们两个是一模一样的？
Do you think the world judges you both the same?
是的 看起来是
Yes. Well, it seems to.
我不觉得 我看到你俩的不同
I don'T. I see the differences between you.
我看向你 见到了你头上的一道光
When I looked at you, I saw a light around your head.
一道光？
A light?
是说… 像光环一样的？
You mean… like a halo?
对 像一圈光环
Yes! Like a circle of light.
你真怪
Ha! You're weird.
我可以吻你吗 琼？
May I kiss you, joan?
早上好 内务大臣
Good morning, chamberlain.
陛下 允许我介绍让-伯雷殿下
Your majesty, may I present his highness jean de bellay,
拜恩的主教 新任法国大使
bishop of bayenne, the new french ambassador.
欢迎你 先生
Bienvenue monsieur.
陛下
Votre majest?
陛下 我很高兴地向您递交国书
Majesty, I am happy to present my credentials.
我很高兴再次跟你国君结盟
And I am happy to be once more friend and ally to your master.
多谢他珍贵的礼物
Thank him for his precious gifts.
我的荣幸
ITS A PLEASURE YOUR HIGHNESS.
那么 阁下 对罗马皇帝之战如何了？
So, your excellence, how is the war against the emperor going?
陛下不必焦虑
Your majesty has no cause for anxiety.
法国军队和我们的盟友热那亚的舰队
A french army and a fleet of our allies the genoese.
已经毫不留情的将罗马皇帝的军队困在那波利
have hopelessly besieged the emperor's soldiers at napoli.
早晚查尔斯将会投降 并撤离意大利
Sooner or later, charles must surrender, and leave italy altogether.
真的是绝好的消息
That is truly excellent news.
啊 阁下 让我向你介绍
Ah! Your excellence, allow me to introduce.
这不是安小姐吗？
is this not mademoiselle anne?
很荣幸见到你
Enchant?
红衣主教沃尔西阁下 跟我讲过你的事情
His eminence, cardinal wolsey, has told me all about you.
但是他没告诉我你是如此的美丽
But he did not tell me how beautiful you are.
作为一个法国人 这可是何等罪过
For a frenchman, that is almost a crime.
但是法国人对所有的女人说她们美丽
BUT FRENCHMEN TELL EVERY WOMAN SHE IS A BEATIFUL.
这不是罪过吗？
IS THAT NOT A CRIME TOO?
哈哈
Ha! Ha!
我给您准备了份礼物
I HAVE S GIFT FOR YOU.
给我吗？
FOR ME?
绝对是送给您的 大人
FOR YOU SIR.
这只狗动作迅猛
THIS DOG IS VERY FAST.
非常的出色
…REALLY FORMIDABLE.
它叫什么名字？
What's his name?
沃尔西
Wolsey.
你会欣喜的 甜心
You ought to be glad, sweetheart.
阁下大人刚刚告诉我 罗马皇帝很快将会被
His excellence has just informed me that the emperor is soon.
击败 并被逐出意大利
to be defeated and driven out of italy.
他将不会成为我们幸福的阻碍
He'll no longer be able to stand in the way of our happiness.
回去找你妻子去吧
Go back to your wife!
谁？居然对国王出言不逊
Who? In the name of the king!
是不是有人说了什么？
Did someone say something…?
这阵臭味是怎么回事？
What is that stink?!
是醋味
It's vinegar!
是醋 阁下
Vinegar, excellence.
发生什么事情？
What's happened?
陛下 城内爆发了汗热病
Your majesty, there's been an outbreak of sweating sickness in the city.
至今日 已有300人丧生
300 deaths, this day alone.
传林纳克医生 快 我的妻子呢？皇后呢？
Fetch dr. Linacre. Quickly. What about my wife, the queen?
皇后怎样了？
What about the queen?
安 别怕 我很快会见到你的
Anne! Don't be afraid, I'll see you soon.
乔治 带你妹妹去她的住处
George, take your sister to her chambers!
快走 快走
Allez, allez!
陛下 从我的经验看来
I find from experience, your majesty,
很多情况下 在实际病症出现之前
that in a great many cases before any actual physical symptoms appear,
患者都会饱受精神错乱之苦
the sufferers undergo a curious mental disorientation,
很快产生恐惧和担忧
a quick sense of fear.
这就是病痛和死亡的前兆
a foreboding of pain and death.
每次幻觉都在扰乱人心
Every rumour sends them into agitated alarm.
确切的说 每个幻觉都能让人们大量出汗
Indeed one rumour can itself cause a 1000 cases of sweat.
所以成千上万并非靠苦力出汗的人 也因恐惧而染上此病
So thousands catch the disease from fear who need not otherwise sweat.
对于遵循健康膳食的人们格外如此
Especially if they observe a good wholesome diet.
健康膳食？
A good wholesome diet?
那就是您的疗法 林纳克医生？不用草药汤剂？
That is your best remedy, dr. Linacre? Not infusions?
汗热症有很多种疗法
I hope your majesty will trust me.
希望陛下您能够相信我
when I tell you that there are countless remedies for the sweat,
依小人所见 近乎所有的方法中 靠用药是无救的
nearly all of them, in my opinion, medically useless.
甚至不可预防？
Even to ward it off?
我听说过一个有趣的理论
Well, I heard of an interesting theory.
与我相熟的一位男士曾经对我发誓
A young gentleman of my acquaintance swears.
他靠运动让身体自然发汗
that he can combat the disease directly.
战胜了汗热症
by working himself.
谢谢你 医生
Thank you, doctor.
我亲爱的妻儿
My dearest wife and family.
这场降临于我们头上的瘟疫 就是上帝的惩罚
This plague that has come upon us, is a punishment from god.
我们都是罪人 而上帝降怒于我们
We are all sinners, and god is displeased with us.
我们的生与死都由上帝一手安排
Whether we live or die is entirely in his hands.
我们所能做的只有祈祷 祈求上帝伟大而无限的仁慈
All we can do is pray and appeal to his great and infinite mercy…
深刻的反省我们罪孽深重的本性
and acknowledge our sinful natures.
并认知自己对上帝的渴求
and our need for his grace.
你认为如何？
So what do you think?
这不就是个出汗的好法子吗？
Isn't that the best way of working up a sweat?
是的 大人
Yes, your grace.
让你丈夫把它舔掉吧
Get your husband to lick it off!
小姑娘 你怎么了？
Child, what is it?
没什么 女士 我…
Nothing, madam I…
我就是觉得有些头晕
I just felt a little dizzy.
过来
Come here.
不用了 我… 我只是有些头晕 我…
No, I… I still feel dizzy, I…
是那种病
that's it!
我染上了出汗症
I've caught the sweat!
才没有 小姑娘
Ha! No gentle child.
只不过头痛 仅此而已
It's just a headache. No more than that.
不是的 我的胃…
It's not! I have… I have pains in my…
很痛
in my stomach.
是的 这不就是症状吗？
Yes! Isn't that a sign?
怎能否认？我就要死了
How can you deny it? I'm going to die!
不 你不会死的 听我说
No, you're not going to die. Listen to me.
你不会死的 好吗？
You are not going to die. Ok?
嘘…
Shhh…
「近日 我可怜的女仆因患汗热症而死去
"My poor maid has this day caught the sweat and died.
在此我恳求陛下 指引我该怎么做？「
I beg your majesty, what shall I do?"
我要去见她
I want to see her.
你建议您不要接近任何染有此病
I would counsel against any contact with infected persons,
或者与染有此病的人有接触的人 您可是贵为英格兰的国王
or those who have had contact with infected persons. You are the king of england.
是的… 但万一她…
Yes… but what if she…
万一她死去该怎么办？
what if she dies?
好了
All right.
转告她 让她立刻离开皇宫
Tell her she must quit the palace,
同她父亲回到西佛堡 务必不得出门
she must go with her father back to hever and by all means shut herself up there.
我会派送草药汤剂给她 帮她护身
I will send her infusions to fortify herself.
我还会写信给她
and I will write to her.
皇后陛下呢？
And what of her majesty?
皇后将会去勒德洛与我们女儿会合
The queen will join our daughter at ludlow.
祈求上帝 让她们在威尔士平安无事
I pray to god they'll be safe enough in wales.
您呢 陛下？
And you, your majesty?
我将闭门留在这里
I will shut myself up here,
无论如何也要避免出汗症的侵入
and keep the sweat at bay with every means.
我可否建议您：
Then if I may advise your majesty:
侍奉您的人越少越好
Keep as few people around you as possible,
以减少您被传染的危险
for in that way you can reduce the risk of contamination.
愿上帝保佑你我
God bless us both.
但愿如此
Indeed.
我前来道别
I've come to say goodbye.
将我送走您满意了？
Are you pleased to send me away?
难道你不想见我们的女儿？
You do not want to see our daughter?
把我送走 您就可以和她一起了？
Are you sending me away so that you can be with her?
不 她…
No, she…
你是说安-博林女士？
do you mean lady anne boleyn?
是的 我说的就是安-博林女士 您毫无避讳
Yes, I mean lady anne boleyn. You make no secret of her.
不是的 她会回到西佛
No she's going back to hever.
她的一个女仆已经死于汗热症
One of her maid's died of the sweat.
您对汗热症的恐惧胜过了您对情妇的痴迷？
And your fear of the sweat is greater than your infatuation with your mistress?
凯瑟琳 她不是我的情妇
Katherine, she is not my mistress.
我没有和她发生过关系
I do not sleep with her.
至少在你我依旧被婚姻所束缚之时 是不会的
Not whilst you and I are still married.
但是您同她说过您爱她吗？
But do you tell her that you love her?
您对她许诺过吗？她让您对她许诺吗？
Do you make promises to her? Does she make promises to you?
还是如您所说 我依旧是您的妻子 您不肯告诉我
Will you not tell me since, as you say, I am still your wife.
凯瑟琳 我衷心的期望
Katherine, I wish with all my heart.
你要接受我们的婚姻是建立在 谎言之上这个事实
you could accept our marriage was based upon a lie.
在这期间
In the meantime,
我依旧爱着你 期望你能保命
I still love you enough to want to save your life.
现在 按我的吩咐去做
Now do as I command.
去威尔士吧
Go to wales.
当您用这样的词藻 我…
When you speak like that, my love…
您的举动好像暗示我得了瘟疫 好像爱情本身就是瘟疫
you act as though I had the plague. As though love itself was like the plague.
我会写信给你
I shall write to you.
请向玛丽带上身为国王 身为人父 的我对她的热爱
Tell mary, the king, her father, sends his love and devotion.
你感觉如何？
How do you feel?
我没事 爸爸
I feel fine, papa.
你确定？
You're sure?
你为什么这么说？
What are you saying?
因为我的女仆出事 我就一定被传染了吗？
Because of my maid I'm certain to be contaminated?
不 当然不是
No, course not.
那到底怎么了？
What is it?
我无法呼吸
I can't breathe.
怎么了？到底怎么回事？
What? What's wrong.
我无法呼吸 停住马车 我无法呼吸 停住马车
I can't breathe, stop the coach. I can't breathe! Stop the coach!
停步 停下马车
Halt! Ho! Stop the coach!
安？
Anne?
继续驾车
Drive on.
安
Anne!
哦 琼… 我亲爱的妹妹
Oh joan… my dear sister.
神父 众所周知 这场病灾是上帝所赐
Father, it is well said and known that sickness is a visitation from god.
是对我们罪孽的惩罚
and a punishment for sins.
但是神父 为什么…
But why father,
为什么我的国土成为他憎恨之地
why is my land so marked out for disfavour?
我们到底做了什么孽 以至万能的上帝如此的愤怒
What have we done that has displeased almighty god so much.
将这场瘟疫降临到我们身上
that he brings this pestilence upon us?
是我的错吗？
Is it my fault?
神父 我恳求上天原谅 这些我们不知为何的罪孽
Father, I ask forgiveness for sins unknown.
并非以一个国王的身份
And I beg you for your blessing.
而是是一个男人的身份 恳请您为我们祈福
Not as a king, but as a man.
求您了 神父
Please father.
神父？
Father?
意大利 奥维多
ORBIETO. ITALY.
两位好
Buon giorno.
你们是英国来的访者？
Are you the english envoys?
跟我来
Prego. Come!
英国来的使者 加德纳先生和福克斯先生
Inviate inglese, mr. Gardiner and mr. Foxe.
我的孩子们…
My sons…
圣父
holy father.
我被迫居住在如此窘迫的环境中 你们也见到了
You see how I am forced to live?
你们能想象到教皇的苦衷吗？
Can you imagine your father's misery?
西班牙人几乎将我击溃
The spaniards are practically.
教皇圣人您知道我们为何来此
Your holiness knows why we are here.
我们带来一封国王亨利陛下的书信
We bring a letter from his majesty, king henry,
英格兰 爱尔兰和法国的国王 最忠实的天主教徒
the most dutiful and catholic king of england, ireland and france.
为了您能废除他的婚约 国王陛下在此提前感谢教皇圣人
His majesty thanks your holiness in advance for your support of his nullity suit.
他知道圣父您不会拒绝他的恳求
He knows that you, holy father, will not object to our supplications.
我诚心的希望
I wish with all my heart.
能够使你们的主子欢欣满意
to please and satisfy your master.
但是我必须跟你们坦诚相见 上帝为证
But I must say to you, in all honesty, as god is my witness,
作为一个诚实的人
and as an honest man,
我已经被告诫 此请求仅仅出于 国王本人对安-博林这个女人
that I have been advised that this suit is prompted solely.
盲目而不正当的爱慕而生
by the king's vain affection and undue love for this woman, anne boleyn.
据我听闻 英国国王只因「私人理由」
It has been said to me that the king of england desires.
擅自要求离婚
his divorce for "private reasons" only,
而且他爱的这个女人 相比之下不仅在身份上
and that the woman he loves is far below him.
在品德方面都过于低微
Not only in rank, but… also in virtue.
教皇圣人… 这些都是谁跟您说的？
Holiness… who has told you these things?
他们说那个叫安的女人已经有了身孕
They say that anne is already pregnant,
并且国王急切的希望让她的孩子 成为继承皇位的子裔
and that the king urgently wishes to make her child his heir to the throne.
安女士是重视贞节的表范
Lady anne is a model of chastity.
尽管她本人也期待生儿育女 但也要等待时机合适之时
Though very apt to procreate children, when the time comes.
圣父大人 她为人之纯洁 珍留至今的处女之身
Holy father, she impresses everyone who sees her or knows her.
为人之冷静 娴熟和谦虚
with the purity of her life.
给所有见过及认识她的人留下深刻印象
her constant virginity, her soberness, meekness, humility.
的确在英格兰诸多女子之中
indeed of all the women in england,
目前为止她是成为皇后的最佳人选
she is by far the fittest to become queen.
但凯瑟琳皇后怎么办？
But what of queen katherine?
陛下他希望
His majesty hopes that,
当教皇圣人您对我们所提出的法律
when your highness has taken cognisance.
论据给予裁决之时
of the legal arguments we have brought with us,
您能写信勒令皇后顺从
you will write to the queen to urge her compliance.
当然
Of course.
但是在得出裁定之前…
But first I must read these arguments… must I not?
我得先过目这些论据 不是吗？
Before coming to judgment.
陛下直接表明他的意思
His majesty also made it plain to us that,
说如果您无法顺其所愿
if you could not give him satisfaction,
他只有去别处令寻定夺
then he must look for a judgment elsewhere.
他将不得不置身于圣主教堂律条
He might be forced to live outside the laws of holy church,
以及教皇圣人您的掌权范围之外
and beyond your holiness's authority.
我的孩子们
My sons.
我的心上人
MY SWEETHEART.
我已经给你送去 很多汗热症的解药 请务必服下…
*******I.
侍童？
Boy…
驾
Ya!
路人小心
People, look out!
驾
Ya!
喔
Woah!
驾
Ya!
我的孩子们
My sons.
圣父
Holy father!
恐怕我的答复要让你们失望了
I fear you will be disappointed in my answer.
关于国王的个案 我无法在此时此地做出定夺
I am unable to make a judgment, here and today, concerning the king's case.
等等 我可没说此事就这样了结
Wait! I have not said it is the end of the matter.
我已决定尽早解决此事…
I am resolved it should be settled as soon as may be…
但是不是在这里
but not here.
你们也看到我现在的状况
You see how I am here!
我指派红衣主教坎佩吉罗为我的行政使节
So, I am appointing cardinal campeggio as my official legate.
只要你国的病灾有所消退 他就会去英格兰
Once the sickness in your country abates, he will travel to england and,
与红衣主教沃尔西组成办事院
together with cardinal wolsey, constitute a court.
听取意见此事的益处所在 并在其基础之上做出定夺
to hear and decide upon the merits of the case.
如果你们的国王如你们所说的那般正直
If your king is as certain of his rightness as you say he is,
那么此次加快他愿望成真的议事
then no doubt he will welcome the proceedings,
一定会受到你们国王的欢迎
which can only hasten the fulfillments of his desires.
进来
Come!
放在那里
Put them there!
陛下应该知道诺福克公爵阁下
Your majesty should know that, his grace, the duke of norfolk,
已经染上了出汗症
having caught the sweat,
假借求医问诊之名要求回到伦敦
asked to be allowed back to london, ostensibly to see a doctor.
我已经代替陛下您拒绝了他的请求
This permission I refused on your majesty's behalf.
陛下您的三个药剂师已经病倒
3 of your majesty's apothecaries have also fallen sick,
同时三个侍应已经过身
while 3 of your chamber servants have died.
您的石匠也已病逝
Your mason redman is also dead.
病灾毫无减退的迹象
The disease shows no sign of abating.
单单在伦敦 已有四万个病例
There are now 40, 000 cases in london alone.
安-博林女士也已染病 但尚在人间
Lady anne boleyn is also sick, yet still survives…
林纳克医生
dr. Linacre!
在 陛下
Yes, your majesty?
安女士患病 安-博林女士
Lady anne is ill. Lady anne boleyn.
速去西佛堡 看在上帝怜爱的份上 救她一命
Go at once to hever castle. And for the love of god, save her life.
小人之见 她已无药可救
In my opinion there is no hope.
生存下去的希望极为渺茫
The vital signs of life are weak and worsening.
病危之际 让牧师守护在她身边吧
The priest should attend her now, in extremis.
我非常的抱歉
I'm very sorry.
你不怕吗 爸爸？
Are you not frightened, papa?
怕什么？害怕死亡？
Of what? Of death?
不 我已经彻彻底底的将自己托付于上帝之手
No. I've given myself entirely into the hands of god,
而且我坚信待我死后
and I know with certainty that.
我可以升入比这里美好的净土
when I die I shall pass into a far better place than this.
亲爱的心肝 你所看到的这一切 不是对死亡的恐惧
What you see around you, darling heart, is not the fear of death,
而是对死后所发生事情的恐惧
but the fear of what, for the unrepentant, must surely follow it.
比起出汗症 一个缠绕住欧洲的恶灵更让我恐惧
There is a spectre haunting europe which I fear far more than the sweat.
那是一种四处蔓延的疾病
A sickness spreading everywhere,
将成千上万的人感染
infecting thousands.
你说得到底是什么 爸爸
Of what do you speak, papa?
就是路德教这种疾病
The disease of lutheranism.
在穷人中不停扩散
It spreads among the poor.
那些人认为教会富有 腐败 而颓废
Those who see the church as rich and corrupt and decadent.
他们在德国挑起了农民战争 死亡人数超过十万
It has already ignited a peasants' war in germany, and killed over 100, 000 people.
这种传染病已经蔓延到了
The contagion has now spread to.
勃艮第 萨尔茨保 蒙彼利埃以及南特
burgundy, salzburg, montpellier and nantes.
每天都有这毒恶异教所传来的新消息
Every day brings more news of the virulence of this heresy.
你确定它不会传到这里来吗？
Surely it won't come here?
哈 它已经传到了这里
Ha! It is already here.
我们获知伦敦市内有秘密会议
We know of secret meetings here in the city of london,
那里的教堂被袭击 遗臭万年的书籍被散播
where the church is attacked, infamous books distributed.
让我来问问你 我的孩子
Let me ask you, my child.
让我来问你
Let me ask you.
如果房子里面有瘟疫 你会怎么做？
What do you do to a house which is plagued with sickness?
用火来消毒
You purge it with fire.
说的没错
Exactly so.
与此同理
In the same way then.
我们必须用火来 驱逐感染我们信仰殿堂的病毒
the sickness which is in our house of faith must be purged with fire.
现在 如你所知 我反对暴力
Now, I am against violence, as you know.
但是我坚信路德
But I believe that luther.
以及他的追随者
and his followers.
应该在此时被镇压 用火焚死
should be seized, right now, and burned.
陛下 众多我们身边的人已经病死
Your majesty, multitudes are dying around us.
近期 差不多牛津 剑桥 和伦敦的人都已患病
Almost everyone in oxford, cambridge and london has been ill recently…
由于主教大人也已病倒
since the cardinal has also been ill,
而陛下您离宫
and your majesty gone from court,
整个王国处于无人统治状态
there is really no government of the kingdom.
城市内已经出现几次暴动 但是陛下您还不必为此担忧
There have been some riots in the city, but your majesty should not be alarmed.
大人
Sir!
快来看
Come and see!
去叫主子
Get the master.
- 主子 主子 - 爸爸 爸爸 快过来
- My lord! My lord! - Papa! Papa come quickly!
乔治…
George…
哦
oh!
你可知道自己做到什么 我的孩子？
You know what you have done, child?
你起死回生
You have risen from the dead.
现在你又可以与国王相见
Now you can see the king again.
一切如以前一般
It can be just as before!
感谢上帝 我的挚爱
Thanks be to god, my own darling,
你从病患中得救 瘟疫也已减退
you are saved and the plague is abated.
我们所盼望的使节在上个周日或周一抵达巴黎
The legate which we most desire arrived at paris on sunday or monday last.
相信下个周日就能听到他到达卡莱的消息
I trust by next monday to hear of his arrival in calais.
相信不久之后 就能共享我们所期待的生活
And then I trust within a while to enjoy that which I have so longed for,
为上帝 为你我祈福
to god's pleasure, and our own.
我的挚爱 无需再为相聚很短而忧愁
No more to you now, my darling, for lack of time,
距上次一吻之后你我分别以久
but that I would you were in my arms, or I in yours,
期待你我紧紧相拥
for I think it long since I kissed you.
安-博林女士给你寄来一封信
You have a letter, from lady anne boleyn.
「我亲爱的大人
"My dear lord,
听到您逃脱病魔毒爪的消息 我非常欣慰
I am delighted to hear that you have escaped the sweat.
我将会用一生的时间
All the days of my life, I am most bound.
去爱戴和效忠
of all creatures, next to the king's grace,
万人之上一人之下的阁下您
to love and serve your grace.
我哀求您 请您相信 只要我上有一口气
I beseech you never to doubt that my opinion of you will ever change,
我对您的看法将永远不会改变
as long as I have any breath in my body.
您卑微的仆人 安-博林「
Your humble servant, anne boleyn."
看来至少她还有些幽默感
Well, at least she has a sense of humour.
安排一下 我要去沃星汉朝圣
Arrange for my pilgrimage to walsingham.
顺便向我们这位女士道谢
I must give thanks to our lady.
感谢您
Thank you.
感谢您 上帝
Thank you god.